Welcome back to a push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. It's been a while since we've
talked about them. So, let's go check on
our good old friends, the South. We've
known up to this point that the South
has an economy that is essentially
entirely based on agriculture. And up
until the Civil War, that agriculture
was essentially all done by slaves. So
now, when the war and reconstruction are
over, a journalist named Henry Grady
sees this and starts petitioning the
South to modernize and adopt the
industrial practices of the North and
turn themselves into a quote new south.
Now, this does gain attention. The North
funds the South to build mills, mines,
and factories, and big industrial cities
form such as Charlotte and Atlanta. But
even with all this industry getting
introduced, this quote new south will
continue to rely on farming and
sharecropping for its primary economic
base. So, on the surface, the new south
is marked by a switch to industry when
in reality, agriculture still remains
the primary economic driver. However,
the other part to this is the role of
African-Ameans. And this is where you
see the big contradiction of the new
south. Because while the south talked a
big game about modernization and
progress, socially and politically, it
was still stuck in the past. White
supremacy didn't disappear at all. And
the clearest example of this is the
Supreme Court case Pie v. Ferguson,
which ruled that racial segregation
laws, known as Jim Crow laws, were
constitutional as long as facilities
were quote separate but equal. In
practice, this whole separate but equal
thing never actually worked out.
African-Americans constantly received
worse facilities, fewer resources, and
almost zero legal protection. Convict
leasing, lynchings, pole taxes, and
unfair literacy tests were all still
very common across the South. Now, there
were people who advocated for
African-American rights, such as Booker
T. Washington, who emphasized economic
self-help and education, and journalists
like Ida B. Wells directly challenged
lynchings and racial violence. But with
these Jim Crow laws now being considered
constitutional, it would be hard for any
real civil rights to appear until quite
a bit later. On the screen now are AP
style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.